foreign
[Music]
is
me
[Music]
oh
foreign
[Music]
me
money
[Music]
foreign
me
[Music]
money
foreign
[Music]
he
hi everyone
ladies and gentlemen
to talk to you about comprehensive
health be it your physical health be is
your beat your mental health and beat
your financial health
it is important to understand that all
top-notch care being available we need
that affordability as well and that is
where
premier eminent and the most respected
loved banks like sdfc bank
and an insurance company health
insurance company like us max bupa we
come in
ladies and gentlemen the best tools
against fight of kobe especially for
everyone in that age group is mask
yourself
maintain a social distance
stay at home unless it unless it is
really necessary to go out
and that should protect you
ladies and gentlemen
we have
nobody but the but the best not just in
india but internationally as well
let me quickly introduce to you somebody
who doesn't need any introduction at all
every citizen of this country knows him
he's not just a figure
of repute just in india
but he is an internationally acclaimed
person
a doctor by excellence dr naresh trahan
dr nardistran is an indian national
is a renowned cardiac cardiovascular and
cardiothoracic surgeon a graduate from
king george medical college and
subsequently trained
and practiced at new york university
medical center manhattan usa from 1971
through 1988
where he obtained the diploma from
american board of surgery and the
american board of cardiothoracic surgery
dr trahan is the chairman and managing
director of
vedanta the
city where he is also the chief cardiac
surgeon
medanta is a very familiar name
an institution
of apex medical care a 1500 bedded
facility multi-super speciality
institute offering cutting-edge
technology and state of our treatment
facilities at an affordable cost
the institute is governed under the
guiding principles i would
create this acromion ccc or 3c which is
based on care compassion and commitment
doctor neri shrahan founded the escorts
heart institute and research center
where he was executive director
it was conceptualized and created and
managed by dr trian from november of 87
through may 2007
he is a recipient of countless
prestigious awards among
which he is a recipient of padmastri
the padma bhushan
presented by the government of india
dr naresh shahan also was the president
of international society for
is invasive cardiac surgery minia police
usa through 2004 to 5e
and also has received honorary doctorate
degrees from three very prestigious
global institutions
please join me in welcoming dr naresh
trayan thank you very much sir thank you
for giving
i would request dr naresh trihan to
first share his thoughts
and i must tell you dr trahan and you
will be immensely happy and feel pride
in the fact that we have more than two
lack more than 200 000 people
on this video call
watching you and listening to you a
record of sorts sir
and everybody is very eager to hear from
you
or in the present context
the present context is to celebration of
senior citizens being the world senior
citizenry but at the same time i can't
help but avoid the current
predicament the situation of kovaid and
nobody more sensitive to the subject
than the senior citizens of our country
your valuable words
will set the context and give a lot of
confidence and information that's
very very essential coming from the top
side over to you sir
thank you and my greetings to
all of you the
uh dr bhavatosh mr rakesh singh the
all the members who are online from
from max from
hdfc and my fellow
senior citizens
so
this is a pleasure and an honor of
course that i being one of one of you i
can
talk to you about
how one feels as we age
so first of all let me address
the
huge crisis that we are in right now
from this unprecedented
virus which we really still grappling
with how to cope with it
so you all know the history of how it
started in wuhan went to some other
countries in the west including
the country like iran italy germany
and then came to india by the way of
travelers who were traveling either from
india
and were visiting there and came back
or people who are from those countries
like the famous 14 italians who were
actually visit uh traveling through
rajasthan and found to have covert 19
that they were rushed to vedanta
and we have been taking care of
perpetuation since then so
it's a it's not a and in a way
a pleasure but it is our duty that we
did it and it's a pleasure that most of
them have recovered and gone home which
is great
so now
we are now in grappling with the fact
that
the last four months what have they
meant for us
so when it came to india
fortunately
the government of india reacted quite
rapidly
and went into a severe lockdown
now
there is a lot of debate whether good
bad medium what it did or it didn't do
but i for one believe that that was
essential and did a huge amount of good
for india and i'll enumerate to you what
happened
so when we discovered that kovit was
becoming like as prevalent in india as
other places we also realized that we
were totally
our infrastructure to deal with this
situation was totally missing
so in other words we didn't have enough
pp's enough masks enough ventilators
enough bed capacity
so that lock down which slowed down the
spread of the virus
broke the chain for a while
gave us that opportunity to be prepared
throughout the country
to a much greater degree since we
started seeing
that our own countrymen our own country
business people came together
and repurposed their industry into
manufacturing ppes and masks and
ventilators and
and beds and everything else that was
needed so in a short period of time we
became self-sufficient and the biggest
pleasure was that we did not have to
depend on a rogue country like china
because this came from china and we
don't know what happened we know that
they did suppress the news for four to
six weeks which did a huge damage to the
world anyway let's park that
the other second benefit that came from
this was
that we expected that when the lockdown
is lifted
unlocking takes place
that there will be a search
but in these three months that the
lockdown was severe
many things happen one for one
the medical profession understood
well how to deal with the virus what is
the pathophysiology
and when where what was the mechanism of
death what was the mechanism of
inflammation in the body and
simultaneously enough drugs were
developed so that at every stage we
could intervene more effectively today
than we could at the beginning
so let's settle the issue
from the medical point of view
lockdown was essential it was valuable
and it has brought us to a level where
we can handle
millions of cases we are now approaching
3 million
but
there is a very high percentage of
recovery
and
many many cases are asymptomatic or
minimally symptomatic so all this has
been possible
because of the
partnership between the front line
workers that is the doctors nurses
technicians
all the other paramilitary forces
along with our
business associates who came to the
rescue by manufacturing all these
equipment in india itself so that it
could be accessible at one fifth the
cost of what was being imported from
china and also this is a first example
of athman nervous that we actually
re-engineered everything in a short
period of time so
that was the second benefit
of of this whole thing
now where are we
from the point that we know
that infection of this
virus
it happens in the following way
there was a study done very early in its
in its inception in the world
that if you take one person who has
coveted infection and you take another
person who does not have infection
they are within three feet of each other
and they are interacting with each other
for more than 15 minutes
then the chances of the person who does
not have the infection getting the
infections become extremely high
however if the person who has the
infection and is wearing a mask
and the other person is not wearing a
mask who is uninfected they are still
within three feet and still a 15 minute
interaction
then the chances become medium
from high
if both of them are wearing a mask
and they are within three feet of each
other and it's a 15 minute interaction
then the chances become minimal
that is the origin of this whole mantra
around the world which says
wear a mask
stay more than three feet preferably six
feet
and the fact that if somebody who has
got it has coughs on their hands or on
the surface you clean your hands and you
clean the surface that's the best
protection you can get okay so we have
been saying this for the last four
months
that this is what needs to be done okay
knowing very well that that was the only
weapon we have against to against the
spread
we cannot kill the virus but we can
actually slow down
the spread if we if we all became
careful which is the example
which is
come down from many countries who went
on a mask day one
and they suffered much less than the
countries where masking was not
encouraged or even discouraged
so
lessons learned
one these three month things of that
mantra that we talked about this is your
dharma
of of masking distancing and hand
hygiene
this will become a part of our life till
we reach that point where vaccine
or some other cure comes out which
prevents all of us from getting the
infection
so let's not even debate whether masks
are needed or distancing is needed
it is needed it is essential
and it is even more so today because we
are unlocking
and we are bringing into mainstream
activity one by one
so now you know that the airlines are
functional the hotels have been opened
the next things to open will be
probably international travel is on the
anvil
then movie halls
then
then other banquet halls so this will
have to happen over a period of time but
carefully thought through
and the more we carefully set the
protocols
the safer it will be
so in other words when you hear
you'll be able to learn learn to live
with the virus
i personally think
it should not be lived with the virus it
should be coped with the virus that we
are coping
we are coping because we are doing
things to protect
our ourselves and our parents and our
children and our society at life so
having said that now he's come to
because of the
our effort to prevention or protecting
yourself
who are the most vulnerable to the virus
and what are the consequence to each
so first of all
any infection
is first fought by your immune system
we knew know
that the immune system
starts from birth
but is a little immature till the age of
10 so you will say the children below
the age of 10
need to be protected because their total
immune system may not be fully developed
yet
then you take the teens to the 50
age group
that immunity time is the highest
and as you cross 60 your immunity starts
going down
so if we studied and which we did at
medanta
what we call
age by decade
unrelated to covid
we did a mapping of how people age every
decade and what should they be doing to
protect themselves at different
inflection points
so once you cross the age of 60
women even 10 years before that because
they reach menopause at 50
your body starts changing and the
changes are the following
first of all your hormonal
system
starts
becoming
weaker in the sense that your levels of
of hormones and enzymes starts
diminishing slowly
the most important thing that happens
after the age of 60 is
that your muscle mass starts going down
unless you
actually uh actually bring it back by
exercising
and that means that vigorous exercise
not just us leisurely walk in the
morning so one of the biggest
misconception is
that i go for a walk in the morning i
walk for one hour yes you get fresh air
yes you do do get de-stressed but does
that mean that your body has developed
muscle enough
to keep your immunity up
so first thing first do not let your
muscle mass go down because that will
start diminishing your immunity
so walk is good brisk walk if you can
cover four kilometers
in 40 minutes 45 minutes that means you
are actually getting good cardiovascular
activity and that is true for everybody
the young and the old together
the second thing is
that you need weights
for your upper body because
walking will not do much for your muscle
building of your upper body
so no matter what depending on
you can start with
with
sort of light weights and then go on and
increase it and increase the frequency
so that if you are doing
walking for 40 minutes
5 to 10 minutes of muscle exercises
yoga being excellent exercise if you do
surya namaskars
you are actually you are a good starting
point
build it up to 30 if you do 30 you don't
need to do any weights
because it will build all your muscles
and muscle is immunity
so one thing specially we always advise
the older people
that the more active you are the better
you are protected and the better and the
least you will age
on the other hand you are stuck in your
house because of the lockdown
so that's even more important that you
should be aware that do not become a
couch potato
you must
move all day
whether it's 10 minutes walking up and
down in a room every hour or two you go
and do that that's fine do yoga
prana pranayama yoga because see one big
thing that kovit has done
and we do not pay much enough attention
to the fact
is the mental state of people
so we know that you're locked up in a
room
concerned about
first
your
yourself or your family or your extended
family
then
your
whether you are going to get affected
and if you are older whether you survive
it or not because you know especially if
you have co-morbidities especially if
you are already suffering from you know
some
autoimmune disease which is
immunosuppression
then you become very vulnerable so you
worry about yourself that is a natural
thing
and then there is an
extreme economic burden on everybody
except the bankers of course
so
though so the point is
that that combination
has created so much disturbance in
people's minds
so their anxiety levels are high
that people have gone into depression
people don't know how what is going to
happen and that is what is disturbing
even more is that we thought that it
will last for three months
now we are counting five months
and it's still not ending
so we don't know how extensive it will
be and how we will come back to normal
or new normal
so anyway the point is
that one we need to take it in our own
hands to protect ourselves
and i would warn especially the young
who feel that i am not vulnerable which
is maybe true to a degree but enough
young people have also
gone gone away from this earth
so don't be cocky about the fact that
you are below the age of 50 that you
nothing will happen to you i mean you
could be that one of those 10 who do get
hurt very badly but more importantly we
have a moral obligation to protect our
children and our elderly
so if you have elderly at home or you go
visit them you have even a double
responsibility because if you infect
them you will never forget you forgive
yourself for the rest of your life
so that's
so much for
immunity by exercise
the second immunity is from nutrition
so because
you there is a tendency because you're
not doing enough activity this tendency
to put on weight and you don't want to
put on weight because you don't want to
put on fat
so that means
that your diet will be verging towards
more protein
some carbohydrate and very little fat
so you make your diet lean
and you make it protein rich
so if you do the three things
nutrition
physical health and mental health that's
the best
you can do to cope with this virus and
prevent it from happening because if
your body is weak
it will definitely get to you if you're
strong there's a good chance that you
may you will not get it or then you will
your body will fight the viral load so
early that you will get a very mild form
of it
so much for your personal life
now
very little i can tell you about wealth
because mr singh is there he will he
will tell you about that
but
next let's go to understanding
what today is the science behind kovid
and why
we how we fight it and why everybody
should understand a good idea of it
because
there is somebody or the other either in
your family or known to you who has
gotten it or will get it
so let me just explain some principles
here
so here is a virus
which of course nobody can see it
it weighs and one thousand ten
thousandth of a
of a grain whatever it does nobody
really knows but the point is
that this virus first enters your body
through the nose and mouth
eyes and all we speculate but i don't
think that there isn't any evidence that
it comes from your mind eyes or ears or
something it comes from when you breathe
it in
so when you say
how does it come
so when somebody has it
unprotected you are unprotected you are
within that person either they are
talking to you or coughing or sneezing
then those droplets come out and they go
inside you you see many pictures on the
tv all the time anyway
the first three four days
once the virus enters
it hooks itself to the ac2 receptor
which is a normal receptor in our body
it's present in every cell that ace-2
receptor
this docs like you know you see the
pictures of international space station
going and docking and coming back and
all that that's exactly what happens
this virus goes the spike that you see
on the violence goes and talks with and
draws new nutrition and multiplies
so your first line of defense is that if
you get greenlit in and it's residing in
your upper airway if you gargle every
day
preferably twice a day with lukewarm
salt water
you can dilute
the mucus here where the virus may be
present
so that is one
possible way of defending yourself
no harm
at least it will keep your throat and
nose clean
and it may even protect you from the
virus so that is one part gargle with
lukewarm water with salt
second
is the point
that
it will go down into your lungs once
enough critical mass has developed
and then it starts affecting the tissues
in your lungs
initially we thought
what the virus does is it goes and
destroys the cells of the lungs
then we discovered not we
40 some
cardiologists and
doctors in italy bergamo
they did autopsies on 50 patients and
found out
that
the mechanism of this virus affecting
the body
is
creating a lot of inflammation in the
tissue
not killing it but inflammation
and when that enough
virus mass is in your body and it goes
and creates the inflammation
then the body reacts and the body reacts
by an immune response which we call
cytokine
now the cytokine depending on the amount
of cytokine that comes out to fight the
virus
is what is the most destructive thing
for our body because it not only kills
tries to kill the virus but it also
destroys or inflames the arteries the
infla arteries get clogged or clotted
and oxygen exchange does not take place
and that's how people die
so having understood that today
as i said one is prevention at home so
prevention of nutrition everything in
the upper airway
gargling i told you so park that aside
now there are some suggestions from the
our grandmother recipes about tulsi and
and galois and all that you can try all
that there's no harm to it
all these ayurvedic things that are
suggested there's nothing wrong with it
it's okay
second comes
that if you get fever
which is high persistent you get a cough
or sore throat
or any difficulty in breathing
or blue lips you see on somebody
must see a doctor right away
if the doctor believes that you have a
very mild case of it and there's no
you're not in the vulnerable group they
may put you on home quality
on home isolation means
that they will monitor you like we have
from vedanta every hospital i think has
one that we have several hundred
patients who are on home isolation
our teams will call them every day
morning evening check their pulse
oximeter temperature
these and all the medicines that we have
prescribed so
a large number of patients
around 80 85
can be treated at home
provided they have isolation facilities
at home
if they don't have then we put them in
what we call covered isolation
facilities which are basically typical
hotels
like
elementary red fox type of hotels where
we have made contracts and and people
can stay there and be be taken care of
the third
stage is that somebody's oxygenation is
going down
somebody's breathing problem or
persistent high fever then we
immediately want to do a ct scan
of the chest
ct scan will tell us immediately how far
is it affecting your lungs
and depending on this if we see a patch
on the lungs
then we must use antiviral drugs right
away
so the antiviral drugs that are the new
drugs that have fortunately been
manufactured in india also so under
licensed from america and japan so one
is the oral pill what we call favi
praveer
which is now as being marketed as
private flu and the second is
with this family
is given by mouth but there are 18 pills
you have to take and all that is not a
very pleasant experience but it has
mid-level anti-viral activity so when in
the early stages you can use five
praveen
or
if a patch appears then we prefer to use
rem deserve which is an intravenous drug
which came from america but is being
manufactured in india by four companies
so there's
enough supply of it so that is what we
need to
start at an early stage
so that we can
decrease the viral load of the body
along with that we know when they reach
the stage where the fever is continuing
in spite of them resume we put them on
cortisone because cortisone reduces the
response of the body or reduces the
cytokine stop
and also we put them on heparin to
prevent clotting so this is today
the standard of care that we call
and should be available to everybody at
least who needs it at this point
then of course there are some
experimental things
like
uh the plasma therapy
also to be instituted early if need be
then there is a new drug to
see we call it tcz
which is also an anti-inflammatory we
are doing a study on it
um along with eight other institutions
are doing that study so we will know the
new things what will help or not help
i would tell you that in our own
experience
more than 50 to 60 percent of the
patients who went on ventilator did not
survive till two months ago
today if you look at it
only
20 of the people
who will not survive
80 percent of people even if they go on
a ventilator can be saved so
our number of people going on ventilator
has gone down hugely as we understand
the disease
so today you can say
two things one
god forbid if you get it and you are
treated in the right hands your chances
of survival are way up in the 90s
so
that's a good news from from very bad
news
now if you want to find out when will it
end
anybody who pretends that they know when
it will end is lying
any doctor
any scientist
anybody i can throw that challenge we
don't know
yes we can give you some guesstimates
the guesstimates are
that say like we we tracked delhi the
delhi was was hit hard along with
maharashtra now delhi is on the decline
and we are seeing that the numbers are
diminishing and we feel that maybe
first 10 days of september or middle of
september we will see it coming under
significant control
mumbai maharashtra is still
not showing that same trend although it
is showing a slow slowing down
but
places like
like hyderabad or say
karnataka
chennai
there
china is still cooling down but those
others are on the upstream
so we don't know
what is disturbing today is
that japan
korea
even germany and france are showing
some resurgence
now that is true
then who who what will happen to
countries like ours we don't know
so that's why i think it's important
that we
keep up our guard
do not
relax
keep your mask i'm sorry i have to keep
repeating it again and again but it has
proven so well that if you want to
protect yourself and go back to work go
back to semi-normal life the new normal
life
please use these protections so with
that i think i've covered fair amount
but if there are any questions left i'll
be happy to answer
uh thank you so much dr treyance that
was very comprehensive
i am sure that
a lot of questions already our senior
citizens and others had in mind is
already addressed in your address and
the details you shared if i made the
summarizer
uh i i heard it clearly from a very
clear messaging point of view
muscle is immunity do more rigorous
exercise even if you walk it should
better be a brisk walk
and
muscle means immunity second thing i
heard is take care of take care of your
mental health and if i may just use the
word be happy to stay you know increase
your immunity i hope that i wouldn't be
wrong in saying so so stay engaged stay
happy stress free
how you achieve it is by physical
activity proper diet and nutrition are
two very important things and at the end
of the day the best tools against bite
of kobe especially for everyone in that
age group is mask yourself
maintain a social distance
stay at home unless it unless it is
really necessary to go out
and that should protect you and the big
silver lining sir i heard is
it is no more as bad as it
was when it started there is more cure
happening today than infection so people
are recovering less and less people are
needing
let's say ventilatory support or icu
admission and more and more requiring so
are recovering because of
the the
the medical fraternity has understood
the disease well there are more
protocols that have been developed in
treating and more and more drugs and
treatment modalities being available
thank you very much for that sir now i
would really like to ask you being
cognizant of your time a few select
questions we have been flooded with a
lot of questions but i know your time is
very precious
uh not just you and your hospital but
the entire medical fraternity the
doctors the paramedics and everybody has
been in the forefront
and recently what i heard uh is that you
know that job is much more difficult job
than a soldier and you have all of you
have our gratitude from the bank from us
at max will find people in general
the reason is
when a soldier goes out to the front he
knows that he may lose his life but the
family of the soldier stays protected in
line when a doctor or a paramedic goes
to the hospital to fight against kobe
it's not just about her or him it's
about the entire family you all are
doing an incredible job except our
gratitude and sincere thanks for that i
will just quickly ask you a few
questions that i have sir and read out
them from a list randomly selected
uh
the first question sir
and this question is from mr mohanlal
chaudhary in bhivani
and his question comes laden with a lot
of personal feeling and emotion and i
that's why i wouldn't do justice if i
did not read it word by what
he is asking how could a senior citizen
maintain his health
when he is not allowed to step out
out of his house
no movement no speaking just isolation
man in the age of 75 plus is usually
surrounded with so many diseases and
needs medical aid frequently which is
unfortunately a lot of times not easily
available in these times
so cut shot he's left for a slow death
and what do you have to say about it i
understand i i see some bit of what you
were you know referring to that
this isolation
causes a lot of stress in mind also and
a lot of that is evident in this
question
so i i'm sorry i didn't unders
understand quite get your last part of
your question you'll have to talk a
little louder because my
the last part was sir
he mentioned that a person of the age of
75 plus is usually surrounded with so
many diseases and needs medical aid
frequently which is unfortunately in
current times not easily available
to cut short is left for a slow death
and what do you have to say about it
because of access to care is so
difficult for senior citizen and i
believe he's 75 plus
yeah so these are very genuine genuine
problems and concerns that the gentleman
has so
as far as being locked up in a small
space
in cognizance of the fact that i said
that you know
yoga is something which you can do
on a mat
four feet by six feet
so you don't really know need a very big
space for that
so
yoga is magical in a way i mean i
practice it myself for the last 32 years
so i i feel i i can say with some
conviction
that it does
not only give you physical
strength it also gives you more mental
and emotional strength
so i think it's a good survival
technique even if you're not doing it
otherwise
for this period it is something worth
worth learning
and now you don't need a teacher to come
home it's online
there are many many programs so i think
that there is there is a lot of benefit
in that as far as being able to access
care for your other
melodies you know like people who have
heart problems who have diabetes who
have other rheumatoid arthritis you know
all those things there has been a huge
huge problem for them and and we are
very cognizant of the fact
that many many more people
have
suffered or passed away
with the fear that they can't go to a
hospital and if they go there
so that's why if you look at it
we have tried to keep our hospitals
totally segregated
from kovid and non-profit
so like in a hospital like ours there's
a totally different tower
where poverty is taken care of and
there's totally full activity going on
uh you know we are operating we have got
everything is going on as as i mean not
to the level that we normally have but
at least 60 70 percent of the activities
going on and patients do come because
many people lost their lives with heart
attacks with burst gall bladders you
know things like that which they
ordinarily would have gone to see a
doctor but were afraid to do so and the
other thing big thing is that people who
suffer the most are the ones who are
locked down in states where healthcare
services are not so great
so to travel from there to institutions
like ours is
very difficult so that's why
it is
i mean we have been one thing i i can
tell you from the way i see it and if
fortunately there is not a second wave
or a third wave
that we will come
we will learn how to cope with it in the
sense that slowly slowly everything is
opening up and the futility of general
lockdowns
has been understood
yes lockdown should be of hot spots
definitely
because that's where it can have benefit
but otherwise trying to knock down the
whole population
is is now
uh not effective and counterproductive
so we need to just educate 24 7
24 7.
mr rakesh singh is here
if you see don't let anybody enter your
banks without a mask just tell me excuse
me
you don't have one let me give you one
so if you if all of us
keep stressing keep
that vigil on we would have done our
country and the humanity a huge service
so i think i'll give you an example i
was we are consulting on airlines how to
allow airlines to operate okay so i was
on on one of the committees
and the initial thing was okay masking
for sure
then the point came i said look you
can't drink water or eat food because
you'll have to take off your mask
and one of the worst thing is eating
drinking water because you know
with the bottle you try to do that and a
lot of people will get a cough from that
and and you will have you will spray the
whole bloody plane with with virus so
once we got the handle on masking
no food no drinking
ma
a shield in front of you and one seat
empty in the middle we knew that's the
best you can do and tell the airlines to
turn up their air circulation to its
maximum
that is the best
way and so far
we've not seen or heard anything bad
happening
from from this travel so that has
emboldened us to say open up the next
open up the next so hopefully over the
next two three months we should have
completed the opening with caution with
with with uh total control on
on everybody trying to protect
themselves if that happens
i think india will survive better than
most other countries especially better
than america which has already always
been careless and suffered for it
right thank you sir
now there is there are many people
asking similar questions
hold it closer to my mouth yes i hope
this is better yeah
many people have a similar question so
i'm just clubbing some of them together
gopal krishna bajaj from bangalore uh mr
vikas bansali from balotra
and
mr rajendra verma from sony path all of
them have a similar question the
question is something you have already
answered to a large extent which is
about how do they take care of their
heart
on daily routine basis and manage stress
and when they speak of stress and many
others are asking this question one
element they are finding difficult these
days is kind of getting good sleep
and that's a complaint that a lot of
people are uh you know asking for some
help with
could you please you know respond to
them help them understand what they can
do
yeah so
as far as if you are don't have heart
disease already
the mantra comes back to
cardiovascular fitness that is exercise
and like i said either you and you are
able to walk briskly even on a treadmill
or in a park or
or or you do i uh serious cars 30 of
them a day
you would keep your cardiovascular
health health in good shape
then comes the point
of how to
take mental keep mental health okay
now mental health is the easiest said
than done
supposing your
your anxiety is whether you you're
you'll get keep your job or will you be
fired or will you be able to pay your
emi or will you
these are things that are very difficult
to cope with
so the problem comes
that how do you
say to yourself you need to build your
mental strength to say i'm not alone
the whole world is down on his knees and
so am i
but that does not mean we will not
recover
so you need to reason with yourself and
reason from outside
the second thing is of course
entertaining yourself
right you entertain yourself
thank god for netflix and
amazon and prime video or whatever else
you have
these are you know
that's that's one thing the second thing
is time with the family
all of us to some degree greater or
lesser me the most are guilty of not
having time for the family so this is
the time when you you will not hopefully
this time will never come again
so you make the best of it
so do find yourself things that you
would like to do which you have not been
able to do because pressure of time
that helps i mean these are all talking
points i mean these are
easier said than done but i'll tell you
pranayama
aloha
is the most fantastic de-stressor you'll
find
so anytime you feel stressed just two
three minutes of breathing exercises
and you will forget about your worries
for a while
and you know two three times a day in
this kind of extraordinary circumstances
is a recommended thing to do
thank you sir sir on a lighter note i
have personally faced a lot of questions
of stress where people has told us that
now we are leaving more time spending
with the family and that's why we are
stressed so that's on a lighter note
which they were not used to
that was purely on a lighter note
uh there is a specific question from one
of our viewers here
who is asking about
he is getting running nose and this is
mr lal young from navi mumbai
he's saying that he's getting running
nose and continuous sneezing every eight
to ten days and it lasts for about two
days he's 69 years old and cycles 20 to
30 kilometers every day and he doesn't
smoke
so obviously obviously he has what we
call allergic rhinitis because
this is what the running nose does
and
there is a you know i keep sorry i'm an
allopathic doctor but i keep referring
to ayurveda and yoga
so niti
is a is a washing system
in yoga
very effective for people with chronic
rhinitis
so maybe he should consult
learn it from from a yoga teacher how to
do that
and gargling every night before you go
to sleep those are the two things you do
90 you'll get cured of that
uh mr
raja maini from panchkula is asking that
is 70
is finding it difficult to walk more
than one kilometer non-stop and he is
getting muscle pains on both legs as he
gets up from the bed in the morning
unfortunately it's very difficult to
diagnose people on a webinar
but i would recommend that if if it is
something chronic then just wait till
the
in bangalore the covet subsides a little
bit but if it is something acute he
should go and see a doctor anyway there
are enough enough hospitals which are
covered free you should go in and see
one of them
so his question is about sir whom or
which speciality should he consult in
so if he's because of this
yeah so if he's having pain in his legs
vascular
cardiovascular even a cardiologist or a
service like a physician or a surgeon
can and can measure everything inside
your legs and be all right
yeah the last question for the evening
okay then i will ask some questions sure
the last question from the for the
evening sir lot of people have
highlighted that they keep hearing about
and reading about sometimes kovi
treatment costing very high especially
in cases requiring icu admission
ventilator support and so on they are
also conscious they write about emerging
treatments like plasma therapy new drugs
that are coming up and overall there is
cost associated with covad
uh for them what is your advice i
understand mr rakes is coming next and
possibly he has a lot of advices for
them which is very practical and useful
and
i may pitch in later from a health
insurance point of view but what is your
advice how do people deal with this what
is the kind of cost they should see
anything that you would advise them
so you see
one thing
although the cost is high
relatively of course if you compare to
any other country or any place where the
quality
you're matching the quality the cost is
about one tenth of what it will cost in
say america or in europe or something
like that but that's not any consolation
for our population because if the cost
is fifty thousand rupees a day
because if you need rendezvous plasma
all the other antibiotics so the cost
does become 40 to 50 000 rupees a day
which is a lot for people okay
and there are although very small number
of people
who will get into the stage where they
have prolonged illness and their bills
may go to 10 15 20 lakhs that you hear
about but that is maybe one percent or
less it's not like everybody has it but
for that person it becomes a big problem
so that's where that's when you should
be able to answer that question being an
insurance man
that for you it would be very simple to
to offer insurance because you know
i'll give you an example
90 of the people who get infected
will be there and
will not need
hospitalization although you have
insured them
and their their home program costs only
15 20 000 rupees for the whole illness
so it's not that the insurance companies
will lose money
if you are hospitalized
even today
even at the insurance rates
the average bill of a patient
really exceeds one lakh for
ninety percent of the people who are
admitted in the hospital
it's that one or two percent whose bill
may reach
three four five seven 10 even 20 lakhs
but that's a that's a very small
proportion so if you were to insure
people
i'm sure
maybe you will not make money
but at least you will be even and you
will provide a huge relief to society
this is the time when all of us have to
think outside of ourselves and that will
take me to the next question i want to
ask mr arkey singh
so rakesh
one of the problems that all of our
senior citizens or a large number of
them
will be facing is what
talked about
how to tide over
this crunch where
they are already on limited income
or maybe no income then only on pensions
so of course there is there is a safety
net
of different varieties whether it is
cghs cchs some insurance that they have
ayushmann is you know for if you are
really
unable to cope with them with it so
those are safety nets that are there
but in this period is it pragmatic
for
say people who do have
a certain amount of ability to pay you
back
to give them a senior citizens
a
bridge loan to get over this kind of
period whether it is for whatever need
it may be
at a lesser interest rate
than
is normally you charge for
commercial transactions is that is that
something asking which is impractical
asking for too much
or
you would say you're already suffering
so much that
we are unable to help
one of the three
but i think uh this is truly a pandemic
so people have to chip in uh in various
manners so
from a pure uh
assistance perspective or financial
resources perspective can be provided
cost is a different element uh depending
on the risk but if children of the
senior students can chip in with let's
say some level of support stroke
guarantee
costs can definitely be lower
uh but yes it is something that can be
possible and uh
clients who have been banking with us
for longer periods of time
obviously have already existing lines of
credit which they can avail from us so
if you're let's say let's say dr srihan
is banking with us for 20 years so you
just don't have to even say we know you
so well so we will have a we will be
able to tell you okay here is let's say
three cross five cross time course this
is what we can give you on on certain
basis
no but as see your lending rate is
probably nine ten percent ten percent
for your preferred customers
but for a three month period or six
months period could it be five percent
six percent or will you be because
that's what you're you're borrowing from
the from reserve bank no so i'm saying
if you did no profit no loss transaction
that would help society usually i'm not
only talking about your bank i'm talking
about as a as an industry if that kind
of bridging
would help
somebody and even the children would be
more forthcoming and say you know i
don't have to pay that much interest on
it
let me help my elderly parents is there
something
something to to think about maybe you
just say okay this bank we as a bank
have put to put aside x number of money
which instead of lending a 10 as part of
our csr we'll do it at five percent
yes sir in certain uh let's say in
certain communities where the needy is
truly needy bank is stepping up we have
a large corpus as you know so we are
stepping up in that those communities
and fulfilling our obligations
but uh depending on a certain case if
there is a community where it is
required we'll definitely look at it but
your suggestion is very welcome that if
we can talk to the central bank and
possibly form a corpus uh to assist that
vulnerable community it's a good idea
actually we haven't thought about it but
maybe still you know this is not going
anywhere for a couple of months more if
it can be done it is it is a good
suggestion because just like uh
rbi has stepped up to uh
help the community uh the cop or the
let's say the industry this may be a one
way to help the community as well
yeah so you know you can choose a cut
off date and say over the age of 65
you know what 60 or whatever it is maybe
because
you know
that will i'm not sure it's going to
make a too much difference into the
three to six month period you bridged
100 crore if you instead of 10 crores
you've got five cross interest
you you five trolls will be nothing for
a bank like yours but you've made a huge
gesture to the elderly community
and
maybe you'll get
return many times over because then we
will all establish that you are you're
elderly friendly
the hdfc bank maybe that's your new ad
obviously sir
there's something we must examine yeah
we must ignore it i wanted to ask you a
question this is your birthday monster
happy belated birthday so
it's not today it was a few days ago but
anyway yes so but the month is there so
happy belated birthday uh
you've been um
very astitude and very agile at
investing i've seen you in that uh
so does the yoga keep you fitter or the
investing keeps you fitter
no these are all see first of all don't
there is such a thing as fake news
don't listen to rumors
in the u.s we used to say
that doctors earn and bankers blow it
away
because of the fact that all these we
never have time to look at our
investments
so basically
it's true that every doctor
i mean who's
made some money
has this thing of trying to play the
market that is a very common tendency
and i have i'm one of the least ones
because i
my time is i mean but i've seen everyone
yeah because other friends and all
they're always talking about
but how savvy they are i don't think so
i don't think they make a lot of money
investing
but uh
it's a roll of the dice i mean where
i've lost enough money in investing
the
and
it's not a it's not a consistent so if
you meet meet somebody see i'll tell you
your business not yours but the
investment bankers business who your
advisor
he will come and tell you
the market went down by 30 percent but
your portfolio only went down by twenty
percent so that's no i mean you
understand the reality but that does not
mean you that your advisor was so smart
that if the market is rising you make
money and it will drop into that and a
fool also knows so there is a lot of
traps in there
and i think
that
best thing to do
is to
you know be very conservative
do not fall for these schemes that some
of the advisors come up with
and
i have i'm speaking from experience
because i've been
i mean carried away by because of lack
of time you don't think properly and you
just say okay if this sounds good do it
but overall i'm wet i'm quite okay
because i don't gamble i don't
really uh so
if once in a while
i feel like i want to pick up a stock i
will
and you luck out and you do well which
is fine and you have one of one or two
of your people who advise me also
and uh have done
reasonably well for me so it's okay
but the excuse always is you know wait
it'll come back the market will come
back
it's a month's game actually
it's a roll of the dice you want to if
you have some money you want to enjoy
yourself do it nothing wrong with it
but don't carry this myth that i am a
very smart investor and i can make a lot
of money yes i'm very
smart in my own field to invest in my
own field yes
yes that's okay
good sir so on behalf of the bank uh dr
really thank you uh thank you for your
time today it has been really wonderful
taking us through the journey of covert
and um i live in bhavato she wanted to
give you a vote of thanks but uh really
on behalf of the bank uh namaskar for
the service
i just tell you
one simple thing
that
there is a
lot of currency for our elder my elder
compatriots to really follow a regime
which means
exercise in the morning
absolutely what i said four kilometers
worth of either walking
and some
upper body muscles
or just vigorous yoga
develop it you can start slow but you
will see that your body responds hugely
things that you've not done in your life
over a period or one or two weeks you
learn how to do it you'll see or you'll
discover your own body is so agile and
age does not matter
aging is directly related to
so as i was telling you muscle mass you
you neutralize
your proteins drop so you must
adjust your diet away from fat more to
proteins
your bone density drops which comes back
with exercise
because you see older people break their
bones easier so your bone density can be
preserved there's nothing wrong your
mental function goes down and the more
you exercise your brain
the better you'll be so don't be passive
watchers of just movies and stuff like
that do whatever you you you know how to
do whether crossword puzzles or play a
game or chess or
play with your grandchildren they'll
keep you
so i think that there is
there is currency so i mean i am
protected by my profession i have to get
up in the morning and get onto my
clothes and come to the hospital so
that's protected but it keeps you going
very well
so i think that one thing that age
should not slow you down
you should slow down your age not age
slowing you down that with that i would
just say it has been a pleasure and
thank you so much
and thank you good to see you
thank you very much sir thank you very
much for your time online
you should you should design some
special packages for senior people
including me
that was quite an enriching quite a
informative session ladies and gentlemen
at this point i would invite mr rakesh
singh
and before i introduce mr raki singh it
is very important that i must tell you
about this important fact
now dr trahan is one of the eminent
doctors he has built the institution as
i mentioned
provides care which was not available
earlier in this part of the world but
today for the most difficult diseases
the best possible treatments are
available here in india
and i have interacted with dr trihan
over last decade in many forums and i
can tell you with conviction
that lot of people in india
do not suffer because the treatment is
not available but because the treatment
for them is not affordable
it is important to understand
that all top-notch care being available
we need that affordability as well and
that is where
premier eminent and the most respected
loved banks like sdfc bank
and an insurance company health
insurance company like us max bupa we
come in
availing treatment and making it
affordable is one part but
making people
do so in a respectable way is another
part
i can talk from my own experience and
experience of others when somebody
suddenly needs to go to a hospital
and needs a treatment and i personally
tested this out and you call people to
say that i instantly need 2 lakh rupees
it's not easy to get that
and no senior citizen who has lived his
life independent
has raised children
made men women out of them has
contributed to the nation building of
this country would ever like to see
themselves in a situation where they
have to basically request somebody for a
help like this
so
the bank not just helps in protecting
and growing your wealth
insurance companies like ours not just
help you protect your health but the
bank and us we also help you retain what
you have guarded
throughout your life that's your
self-respect let me welcome mr rakesh
singh and a quick introduction
mr rakesh singh is a very senior
seasoned professional
he is the group head of investment
banking private banking capital markets
and financial institutions at sdfc bank
india's premier bank
mr rakesh joined the bank in the year
2011 and has been instrumental in
setting up the investment banking and
project finance businesses for the bank
rakes has over 27 years of experience in
managing client relationship
debt and equity market capital markets
structured finance leveraged finance
debt restructuring and managing
proprietary investments
prior to journey joining the bank
in the year 2011 he has worked with all
the noted financial reputed institutions
like rothschild
morgan stanley dsp maryland standard
chartered bank and ang investment bank
he also serves as a trustee on the board
of sneha
society for nutrition education and
health action
ladies and gentlemen please welcome mr
rakesh singh
good evening and namaste
greetings from the bank
from our side we would like to welcome
all our senior citizens to dc uh to this
webinar
we are fortunate to hear dr trehan
earlier
he's possibly been a gentleman who will
be on the television right through this
whole pandemic and has guided us
on behalf of the bank we sincerely wish
that all our clients
and all their loved ones remain
safe and healthy during this pandemic so
this is our
is our wish that you all remain healthy
and
may you see the passing away of this
pandemic very safely
one of the things with dr trehan said is
that you got to be happy in this
pandemic and
it is very
very interesting to see that
money is one element of buying happiness
but not the only element that can buy
happiness so i just go as googling for
this uh for this webinar and i came
across this
thing called uh money can't buy
happiness and that led me to the un
world happiness report and very i was
very intrigued to see that finland
happens to be the
happiest country in the world for three
decades in a row
and
why so you know it's very interesting
why so so it all boiled down to the
quality of life at finland
very cool uh
very you know not a very easy uh climate
to live in but why so uh
why was uh
is such a happy country
so
we found that
there were
five factors you know which which came
across um
why people in finland were very happy
one of them was that they had the
freedom to make their life choices
they were had trust in their social
institutions they had trust in their
political institutions
the life expectancy
was
longer they expected to live healthy
they had great level of support from
family and friends and above all the
community had a sense of generosity
there was generosity within the
community
further you know delving deeper they
found out what we saw this time actually
in certain parts of india especially i
come from bombay so we saw it in dharavi
there was a high trust within the
community and the community was very
self-resilient the very very resilient
community
and people living in these communities
had they formed a social fabric so in
times of misfortune they could get
together and support each other
so
staying happy uh
it comes from the social fabric i think
in india joint families have existed
and i hope that this culture continues
to you know help us in this pandemic to
stay happy and stay united together
right uh
when i move on to uh wealth management i
also wanted to uh share an incident with
you it is i was very fortunate to meet
one of the leading movie stars recently
uh
early part of the year so when i met him
and i was reading his profile um
i saw his 60 years of age so i um when
when i met him he looked uh a shade
younger than me i'm 51.
i thought great
so we will serve coffee so i asked him
impromptu is this does this coffee have
sugar he said yes uh is it this filter
coffee does have sugar it says low sugar
or full sugar full sugar
i say excellent so i said you're 60 or
you have any dietary pattern no dietary
absolutely i lead a very healthy life
it prompted me to ask
being a professional i said what is your
life all about he says listen i sleep
eight hours a day so i at the lot of ten
i'm in my bed and i get up at 6am in the
morning
followed by an hour of exercise
8 am sharp i eat my breakfast and then
prepare and read my script for the first
two hours between 8 and 10. at 10 i get
ready and leave for my shoot
at 12 i eat the regular lunch which all
of you eat
i eat my i have a snack at about four
and i eat my dinner at seven
just before just around sunset but don't
eat anything after that
so it prompted me to ask questions what
happened to your party right here film
stars do a lot of parties well that is
only on saturday night
okay nothing else i only do that on
saturday night
and uh he's 60 61 he looks so fit uh so
fit that amazed me so i realized that
this whole
time allocation and diet allocation was
very important so it came back to our
world of investments and and the very
important fact in the world of
investment is asset allocation no asset
allocation
and on the subject of asset allocation
i'd like to bring in a very pertinent
investor called ray value
the gentleman who wrote a book called
the principles the principles is the
book written by him he manages a 150
billion
hedge fund called bridgewater
associates and they decided this a
portfolio called all weather portfolio
the always the portfolio in the us has
55 percent in bonds
30 in u.s equities and 15 percent hard
assets called gold and commodity which
basically is golden commodities
what they have seen over a period right
they started this you know
structuring this portfolio from 1976
until 1996 1975 and 1996 and 21 years
they actually optimized their portfolio
and after optimizing they've seen that
these the portfolio has returned till
now ytd somewhere eight point one one
percent till date
very interesting to see that so then
they dissected the portfolio how did
they manage this whole thing and uh it
was interesting to see that when the
markets are expected to fall like what
we just saw in the pandemic
bonds do very well so you saw the bond
yields actually moved down
in indian context also we have seen the
bond yields coming from let's say 640 to
all over about 580 odd
and hence bond funds make a lot of money
however when you expect growth or when
you expect inflation then stock markets
tends to get better returns than bond
markets and hence the stock allocation
of the portfolio does very well
so according to senior citizens here i
think what you would like to suggest is
that when you are experimenting and
you're looking at
keeping a study very stable stable
portfolio i would recommend that uh from
a investment perspective 60 to 60 to 70
percent of your portfolio should
comprise of fixed income
bond funds reits invents
giving between six and seven percent of
return currently they've become lower
because of reduction interest rates
you may
also to keep as dr three hundred uh
saying that some interest in the stock
market keep your mind live put something
in the large cap funds which show lesser
volatility
uh between 10 11
and keep uh which currently gives 10 11
so allocation should be between 20 and
30 of the large cap funds
and on the mid cap funds and maybe gold
you can stagger and put somewhere
between 10 and 20 of your wealth
this is this asset allocation is some
similarly like the diet allocation and
the time allocation of this south indian
movie star which i met
who at 60 looked fifth uh 49.50 so i'm
sure uh this at this
asset allocation also give you some kind
of a similar feeling
i have often been asked a question and i
was at a seminar in chennai um and this
gentleman got up and asked me this
question you know but this is very
simple uh
i can also do this so what is the advice
in this so i said uh but why can't you
tell me to invest more in mid cap and
small cap that is where you make the
return that's what i deemed advice for
so i was very prompted to say said you
know
have you been to a roller coaster
ride he says yes
so i said do you love it he said yes
but for how for how long he says five
ten minutes so i said if you invest in
a lot of your money in mid cap and score
small cap funds the ride in the roller
coaster is a little longer than 5 and 10
minutes so it gives you volatility it
gives you a little bit of heartache but
if you can withstand it is fine that
example made you understand that when
you do invest in mid cap and school
small cap companies you need to have
that level of
you know allocation right
this allocation is right for senior
citizens people who have higher risk
appetite or higher appetite to
experiment and you know
wait for longer duration
they must invest in higher growth
companies in which individual stocks but
people who are in the senior citizen
bucket may look at a very balanced level
of asset allocation per se
coming back to indian markets what we
are saying is a very interesting shift
actually uh there is a
shift in the underlying indian economy
uh i will give you some data points
which would be very interesting for a
very
uh i could have given you more but i
just stick to something which i'll give
you is very relevant
jan 2018 12 uh 13 years back you know
the oil and gas index was all oil and
gas
uh
composition in nifty was 25 percent
metals in mining was eight percent
14 percent was the allocation of
construction cement and cab goods so if
you put the
this economy which is oil and gas
metals
cement cap goods and construction
you come to a ballpark allocation
somewhere between 45 and 50 percent
fast forward today
if you look at the allocation of nifty
to the kind of sectors
your banks are at 30 percent which you
are 40 prior to the pandemic but now at
30 percent
and i t and technology is a third is is
that an equivalent weightage of 30
and pharma is another 20
so
we are clearly seeing a shift of
allocation of capital in the stock
market
away from old economy industrial economy
to
services and knowledge economy and that
is happening because most of the
businesses are becoming capital light
there they want to have lesser leverage
lesser loans
they are focused on higher higher roe
and
technology itself is bringing a lot of
change
around us so
industrial economy is getting definitely
a lesser allocation of capital as we go
ahead in terms of our own view on the
markets i think uh
we would advise we have
we we believe that
further allocation of the stock market
to it pharma
chemicals insurance
cement consumer durables larger
corporate banks is something which you
must look at our investors must look at
the arthur nervous scheme of the
government of india
the pli scheme
will definitely be beneficial to
chemical companies
they will also be beneficial to
companies which are in the industrial
economy
they will give that one time liftoff
and people should definitely look at
investing across market caps as we were
talking earlier so a larger allocation
to large cap
and a smaller allocation to mid cap and
small cam
so just to summarize this thing uh dr dr
treyhan said muscle is immunity
so in case of financial markets asset
allocation is that muscle which provides
you that immunity right so then you may
have the you you may have challenges but
uh it is that the acid allocation is the
muscle that provides you that immunity
the second thing he told about is stay
engaged and stay happy
so how do you stay engaged and stay
happy is by going down to ensuring that
when you are allocating you allocate
very properly you understand what your
risk appetite is and accordingly fit
your investment patterns into that
appetite and that allocation
uh we also said very interestingly in
pandemic uh just ensure that you don't
you wear a mask and kept total distance
every bull run brings that pandemic in
the stock market so when in the bull run
we always everything is rising like real
estate prices rise or something like
that so you got to ensure that you keep
that social distance in that in that uh
bull market to ensure that you
invest rightly and don't lose money
because losing money
is is is
getting that capital back is a very
difficult task
so on this note i will thank all of you
and uh
handed over to bhavtosh
if he has any questions
thank you rakesh uh let me ask you a
very important question and this will be
in the minds of many of the bank's
customers what special products and
offerings does the bank sdfc bank have
for senior citizens
so uh i think we have if you look at the
bank's product offering i think most of
our
ultra hnis
generally bank with us we offer wealth
wealth products as such
we recommend a lot of annuity driven
products currently because the insurance
companies currently have come up and
they are offering a
fairly attractive annuity schemes uh
which gives you which give your tax free
yield in the vicinity of five and a half
percent you know it ranges from five to
five point something to maybe something
at five point six five point seven
percent as well so we definitely
recommend people to look at annuity
schemes who especially are just retiring
because they can actually take this
one-shot annuity schemes and if they're
in a higher tax bracket
the second thing we recommend is a
allocation into
fixed income products per se so maybe
they put some money in fds with the bank
to keep the liquidity they can put some
money in the bond funds as such
and obviously we have the senior citizen
deposit scheme which is our hit product
where we pay where the deposit rates are
higher and
they must experiment that and i'm sure
people who want to be associated with
the capital market it's good to put some
money in mutual funds as well
it's good to go with fund managers
because it's helpful from uh from a
perspective that
they fundraisers have the ability to
dynamically allocate assets across
across various market cycles and the
hence they reduce the actual volatility
in the hands of the investor
interesting question luck is that people
want to understand
that
how safe are corporate fixed deposits
because they are giving a relatively
better return as compared to bank fixed
deposits is it safe
see corporate depends on the nature of
the property you pick up you know you
you've seen variety of corporates so if
you talk to the larger corporate houses
in the country so they're definitely
reasonably safe but there have been a
string of uh other corporate employees
which have come from not so strong
companies so if you are investing in a
triple rate corporate fda yes obviously
uh i would say it is safe but when you
are going down the risk chain uh the
risk increases
tremendously so you got to compare a
bank deposit which is fairly liquid
very liquid you can come to the bank at
any point of time you can take a
premature catchment
you can take a loan against eft if you
want to
so a lot of facilities are there you
know and when you build a track record
with the bank in an exchange in an
agency when you need money you can
always provide money and liquidity
against that ft as well
so
a triple a a triple a fd or a bank fd is
good you can't say the same thing about
a cooperative person another cooperative
person
as an ace
seasoned banker uh what would be your
advice to somebody who's just retiring
with a corpus in terms of a location
well we discussed this uh uh as a part
of my conversation i think 60 70 should
go into fixed income uh funds basically
fixed income fixed income yielding
products whether they are essentially uh
bond funds or there are annuity schemes
or the leads in which something which
gives them a yield of six to seven
percent currently in that vicinity uh
some of them will be taxed on them some
they will be taxable uh depending on the
holding period so if you are holding it
for three years of corporate bond fund
then the tax liability reduces to that
extent uh 20 to 30 in large cap funds
and 10 to 20 percent in mid cap small
cap which gives you if you get the if
the fund might get the cycle right and
get the skip script choice right then he
definitely makes a higher return for you
so
your recommendation on the overall
equity exposure for a senior citizen all
exposures put on equities
30 to 40 uh not more than that
and as you go older as you grow older it
should keep reducing so
60 60 percent fixed income 70 70 fixed
income 80 is 80
fixed income that way
certainly that will be very useful to
our senior citizens something i would
take from dr treyance and rakesh's
advice and very very wonderful important
inputs is that
health is comprehensive it does not have
one side there are many aspects to
health physical health
mental health and certainly financial
health and
no better than sdfc bank the premier
bank of india to be your partner in that
you are in the safe hands and it is
important to be in safe hands because i
have personally and we have done
research to see in these times which are
volatile all that you need is trust more
than ever
and there is nobody more
that you can trust than sdfc bank
you must diversify your portfolio and
how to do that is something we got to
hear from the best in the industry
i would add that health insurance is an
important element
you must consider health insurance uh
i'll give an example of a
recent product called reassure that we
launched which has very little waiting
period for uh kovid and it is an
exceptional product so please invest
wise invest with the best the ones that
you can trust uh i'm sure these are very
very important actionable inputs to you
uh thank you ruckus for
for for your insights and your time i'll
quickly move to
requesting all of you customers
and participants
to a poll
you please take part in this poll but
before that there is a health and
wellness help desk open to attendees on
21st of august between 4 30 pm to 7 30
p.m and on 22nd august between 10 a.m to
6 p.m
where the attendees can reach out to the
bank for
queries on wealth and queries on health
you might like to note down the numbers
for wealth it is zero double to
four eight nine
six eight triple two i repeat it is zero
double two
four eight nine
six eight
triple two and for health queries you
can reach out at
zero eight zero
four seven one
eight nine seven
three six
i repeat
zero eight zero
four 471
so thank you very much and please stay
please participate on the poll that is
going to run for you it is important
please stay online
you